Welcome, my name is Thomas Niegloed from Norsk Forening for Quantitative Finance.
Great to see that so many people showed up here today for our seminar.
So we have a, yeah, the first I will start by saying something shortly about our association.
After that, we are very proud to have with us Professor Marcos Lopez de Prado, who will present his latest book.
Marcus Lopustoprado is the CIO of True Positive Technologies.
Before that, he was head of machine learning at AQR.
He's written two bestsellers about machine learning for finance.
After the presentation by Marcus of about 40 minutes, he will answer questions.
So there is a possibility for all attendees to write questions in the Q&A, which we will read to Marcus after his presentation.
After the first hour, we will then have the final for our call for papers.
We have a call for papers sponsored by NURPONT.
There will be four finalists who will present their papers.
We have a jury here who will select the winner who will receive 20,000 kroner and a possibility for an internship with NUACON.
But before we start with this agenda, let me just say a couple of words about the reason why we are here.
And that's our association.
NOSKVD for Quantitative Finance is a relatively young organization, but we feel we've accomplished quite a lot already.
The goal of the association is to promote a quantitative research-based method in finance.
We're also an open association.
We aim to include not just the financial industry, but also academic environments, academia, students, research institutions, and investors.
We have been quite active on LinkedIn.
on LinkedIn. So most of you probably know us from there. We have a LinkedIn page and
two groups mainly for Norwegian financial professionals It quantitative finance with well over 2 members and machine learning for finance with well over 1 members On our website NFKF you can read more about our activities our board and it possible to subscribe to our newsletter
Our main activities have been seminars.
So last year, we had eight seminars with close to 1,500 participants.
this year we started out with two seminars
but of course because of the coronavirus
situation it's been more quiet
this is our first
webinar and we're quite happy we have
several hundred
registrations for this webinar so it's
a great start for us
for our online activities
if any of you
participating here attending
is interested in organizing a seminar
please contact us
so we have a busy
schedule here today, so I suggest I give the word to Professor Marcos López de Prado.
Welcome, Marcos.
Thank you, Thomas.
It's a pleasure to be here.
Today, I would like to discuss a very important problem that we all face in investments, and
that's how can we allocate assets, how can we build portfolios that are diversified and
that are providing good performance out of sample.
So this is a problem that originated earlier on
in finance in the 1950s.
That's where when Harry Markovich made his great breakthrough
of how to develop portfolios that are well diversified,
where we can obtain a high level of return subject
to a certain level of risk.
And that gave birth to modern portfolio theory.
Over the past 70 years or so,
this has been the benchmark for most firms
who approach the problem of asset allocation
from a convex optimization perspective.
Now, we have to understand that there are a number of pitfalls
associated with this approach.
As valuable as it is,
it is very well known that
convex optimization solutions in general are unstable they lack robustness and the purpose of today seminar is to introduce machine learning techniques that help us address
many of these caveats. So we can summarize the two sources of instability that we observe in
portfolio optimization as to number one, noise induced instability. This is instability that
is associated with noisy inputs, noise in the company's matrix, noise in the vector of expected
returns, but then also signal induced instability. This is a far less known and often misunderstood
source of instability as we will see in a moment.
But first of all, we need to understand the problem.
Let's state the problem that portfolio construction
and convex optimization solutions to portfolio construction try to solve.
Suppose that you have an investment universe of 10 assets.
These are random variables where the expected return of those variables
is described by an array mu and the covariance matrix models the
codependence between these variables. The objective of complex optimization is to
minimize the variance of the portfolio represented here as objective function
subject to achieving a certain level of return or some other condition that we
want to establish. Typically this is expressed in terms of return but
sometimes you can introduce here some other constraint which is characterized
by this array A also known as the characteristic vector. Typically in a
The convex optimization problem with equality constraints, you can solve this using Lagrangians.
The important piece of information in this slide is at the bottom, where, as you can see, the optimal portfolio results from the product of the inverse covariance matrix with the characteristic vector.
this is problematic because if the matrix is unstable is numerically conditioned its inverse is going to magnify any of the errors associated with noise in the vector of expected returns or in particular but in general with the characteristic vector
So think of a covariance matrix that is numerically conditioned.
This means that the determinant will be small.
As a result, V inverse is going to have some numbers that explode because these numbers are divided by another number that is very close to zero, the determinant.
And as a result, any error incorporated in A is magnified by V inverse.
the solution also happens to be a minimum, which we can verify through the Hessian of the problem.
Now, the numerical instability appears because we do not know the true V and we do not know the true A.
We only have estimates.
So we replace in this optimal solution VNA with their maximum likelihood estimates.
And that's where the solution, which is mathematically correct, now happens to be in practice problematic.
The two kinds of problems that we will examine next is noise-inducing stability and signal-inducing stability.
So what is noise-induced instability? To understand where noise-induced instability comes in, we need to review a little bit of random matrix theory.
So, again, consider that you have your investment universe of size n, you have t observations, so the x matrix of observations is of order t by n.
and further suppose that these variables are random and the observations are independent
and identically distributed. These observations will have a mean of zero and a variance of
these observations will have a mean of zero and a variance of sigma squared.
So if the observations of the portfolio do not have a zero mean,
they can be easily centered.
The variance of the observations will be sigma squared.
Well, this means that matrix C can be computed as x prime x divided by the number of observations.
and that represents the covariance matrix.
Now, applying random matrix theory, we know that as n grows,
the number of columns in the X matrix grows and the number of rows in the X matrix grows.
as long as this ratio T divided by N is greater than one,
the Marchenko-Bastard theory tells us that the probability distribution of the eigenvalues
associated with this matrix C will follow this function.
The important implication of this is that when we compute the eigenvalues of the covariance matrix, we will observe that these eigenvalues are bounded between two levels, lambda minus and lambda plus.
And the important expression in this slide is to recognize that both the lower bound of the eigenvalue and the upper bound of the eigenvalue are a function of this very important expression, n over t.
When we have many columns relative to the number of observations, lambda plus increases and lambda minus decreases.
It means that the distribution widens as we increase the number of columns relative to the number of observations.
Why is this important?
Well, it is very important because it means that when we have a relatively smaller number of observations,
now the lambda minus will become smaller and eventually it will become very close to zero which means that the determinant will be very close to zero As you remember from linear algebra the determinant is the product of the eigenvalues So what can we do about this
Well, we can fit the given equivalence matrix that comes from VARA or any
other vendor or that you compute yourself, what we can do is we can fit the eigenvalues of that
covariance matrix to the Marchenko-Bastogh distribution and you will obtain a plot like this.
This plot will indicate an area under which the large majority of the eigenvalues fall.
These are eigenvalues associated with noise. Why? Because the Marchenko-Bastogh distribution
is the distribution of the eigenvalues of a random covariance matrix. So all randomicity,
all sorts of noise falls under the Marchenko-Pastor distribution, then there will be a gap.
Beyond that, there are some eigenvalues that are too large, too strong for being associated with
noise. The Marchenko-Pastor distribution, when fitted properly, allows us to separate
the eigenvalues associated with noise from the eigenvalues associated with signal.
And this is very useful because it means that now we can denoise the
Kubernetes matrix. What do I mean with denoising? Well, since the eigenvalues
that fall under the Marchenko-Bastard distribution are associated with noise,
we can transform them in any way we want. They do not carry information.
we can transform in any way we want in order to improve the numerical properties of the covariance matrix.
So one approach is to take any of the eigenvalues that fall under the Marchenko-Pastor distribution and replace them with their mean.
Why with their mean? Well, because we want to preserve the trace of the covariance matrix.
And as long as we replace these values with their mean, the sum of the eigenvalues will still equal the trace of the original covariance matrix.
While we accomplish the goal that the minimum eigenvalue is now equal to the mean eigenvalue under Marchenko which means that it will be larger than lambda minus the lower bound of Marchenko So this is what we call the constant residual eigenvalue method We just as you can see in this plot
we take any eigenvalue below that is below lambda plus and we replace it with the mean
here in log scale, which means that there is a point beyond all eigenvalues are constant.
And as you can see, the smallest eigenvalue is much larger than the original smallest eigenvalue.
So this accomplishes the goal that now the determinant of the covariance matrix
is way larger than the eigenvalue of the original covariance matrix.
The second approach is to shrink the covariance matrix associated with noise. Essentially,
we can form a covariance matrix associated with the marching capacitor distribution,
with eigenvalues under the Marchenko-Basler distribution and that's what we're going to shrink.
So rather than applying L'Edouard-Wolfe's style of shrinkage to the entire covariance matrix,
what we will do is we will shrink only the eigenvalues associated with noise.
This has the benefit that, as you can see in this plot, all the eigenvalues associated with signal
remain essentially unchanged. So we do not lose signal, but we are able to remove a lot of the
noise. Now there is a second transformation that is very useful and that's detoning.
The idea of detoning is that there are certain eigenvectors associated with risk vectors.
In fact, there are some risks associated with that impacts all of the variables in the system.
You can think of sectors or market or region-based risk.
So these risks impact all of the securities which means that these risks are not particularly useful in terms of allocating assets between one group and another Why Because if everything is exposed to the market well this does not help us much in terms of differentiating security A to security B
We still are interested, of course,
in the degree of exposure,
but most stocks, for instance,
exhibit a very high correlation to the broad market index.
This means that information about the market risk
is not particularly helpful in terms of discriminating between the various securities.
So the idea here is we are going to remove the broad market exposure.
And after we remove that dimension, we can do an allocation for the rest.
It is essentially the same as if you are in a public place, let's say in a party, and there is a background noise.
this background noise doesn't allow you to hear a conversation.
So what you would like is to cancel the background noise so that you can amplify the information that you are getting from a different channel.
So the same happens here. We can remove the market component, typically the first or second principal component,
and then we can do an optimization on the rest.
Whenever we remove one dimension to the system, it means, of course, that the correlation matrix is not going to be invertible.
In fact, it will be singular. But that's not a problem.
What we can do is we can do the allocation on the reduced system and then we can map back those allocations to the original system using the eigenvector matrix.
Well, does this approach work?
there are essentially two ways we can evaluate whether these methods work in
practice. One would be to run a number of historical simulations and another
approach is to run Monte Carlo experiments. In this case I'm running
Monte Carlo experiments. Why? Because the question is whether this approach works
mathematically. Does this approach have good mathematical properties? A
A historical simulation would give us anecdotal information as to whether a particular approach
would have performed for a single path, the historical realization.
not powerful enough, a historical practice is not powerful enough to reach a conclusion as to whether
a particular approach works mathematically or not. In statistics, whenever we want to evaluate the
characteristics of an estimator or a particular model, what we do is we run Monte Carlo experiments
because we want to understand the properties of an approach while controlling for the conditions of
the system. So what I've done here is I've generated a coverage matrix of size 500 by 500,
which is representative of the S&P 500, and I've added a market component,
I've added sectors components, so there are essentially 10 clusters of stocks,
one representing each sector of the economy, and then what I've done is given these ground truths,
covariance matrix, we can sample covariance matrices. So for each we can sample 1,000 observations
from the ground truth and form a covariance matrix and then another thousand observations
form another covariance matrix. In that way we can generate thousands of random covariance matrices,
all of them drawn from the original ground truth.
And for each of these random covariance matrices, we can apply Markovits' style optimization.
For instance, the standard critical line algorithm.
And for each of these critical line solutions, we can compare the result with the original, the result that comes from the ground truth that gives us the estimation error.
So this Monte Carlo approach allows us to derive the bootstrap of the estimation error.
And we can do that for the critical line algorithm,
and we can do this also for the approach that I just described.
Essentially, we would apply first denoising, and then we would apply Markovitch.
And the question is by how much does denoising increase or decrease the estimation error That can be evaluated by computing the root error of this Monte Carlo So what we find is that when we compute the
minimum variance portfolio, denoising helps a lot. It reduces the root-minus-square error by around
60%. While L'Edoard Wolf
stylish shrinkage would also be beneficial. It would reduce by
about half of what denoising accomplishes.
When you use both methods combined, there is no
additional benefit. Essentially, it improves a little bit over
what you would obtain with denoising,
but not by much.
so in that sense it appears that denoising benefits from all the risk reduction of
ledouin wolf and more in fact the risk reduction is 60 percent as opposed to 30 percent
how about the maximum sharp ratio portfolio well here the reduction is even more impressive
you will obtain when you repeat this study at home you will obtain that
denoising accomplishes around 94% reduction in the root mean square error.
So if you're familiar with financial solutions, typically even a small improvement is meaningful.
After all, in finance, we are always looking after the small edges.
And in this particular case, we are talking about a 94% reduction in the root mean square error,
meaning that denoising is a practical and very efficient way of stabilizing the fishing frontier.
But as I said at the beginning, there is a second problem that is often misunderstood, signal-inducing stability.
How can signal be a problem?
Very often we associate signal with information that we want to capture.
Signal is our friend.
how could it be that signal is in fact detrimental to our efforts? Well, let's
explain it with a small example. Consider a correlation matrix of 2 by 2. This
means that there are some of the, there is an off-diagonal element here, rho. When
we compute the eigenvector decomposition this is the eigenvector these are the eigenvalues As you can see one eigenvalue is 1 plus rho the other eigenvalue is one minus rho What this means is that when we compute the trace of the correlation matrix
it has to be two, of course, because the trace, the diagonal of the
correlation matrix is an array of ones. In this case, it will be
two and that's equal to lambda one one plus lambda two two.
So when we increase one eigenvalue, it can only come at the detriment of the other eigenvalue,
because this expression must remain true. When we compute the determinant of the correlation
matrix, what is the product of the eigenvalues, which is one minus rho square? So let's think
of what these two expressions mean together. What it means is that the determinant reaches its
maximum when the two eigenvalues are equal to one, but that's only true when rho is zero. So, unless
the correlation matrix is an identity matrix, there will be a decay in the determinant. The
determinant will become smaller and in fact, as we can see, the determinant could be zero if rho is
equal to one. When rho increases in absolute value, the determinant becomes very close to zero.
The second conclusion that we can observe here is that the determinant, in fact, when we compute the
inverse correlation matrix, the inverse correlation matrix is a function of the
determinant here. So as the determinant becomes very small, the values in the inverse correlation
matrix explode. And that's the problem that we observed at the beginning. How is this different
from noise-induced instability? Well, we have reached the same conclusion, meaning that the
solution to the efficient frontier is going to be unstable, but following a different path.
In this case, we reach this conclusion regardless of the ratio n over t.
Remember that when I introduced the Marchenko-Passeur distribution,
I pointed to the fact that lambda plus and lambda minus were a function of n over t Here as you can see the inverse governance matrix is going to explode even if t is an extremely large number
It doesn't matter what the ratio is of n over t.
The explosion occurs as a result of the value of rho.
So this is not noise-induced stability.
This is signal-induced stability.
And even if we have trillions of observations, the system will be unstable as a result of raw.
And raw is signal. Raw is the information that we utilize.
Even if we know the true correlation matrix, the system will still be unstable.
This is what I call Markovitch's course. Why? Because Markovitch's approach is extremely useful.
There is no doubt that it is one of the milestones in investments and in finance.
But we need to understand that Markovitch was developed for the purpose of modeling correlations.
And when we have a correlation structure like the one that we have observed before, where the off-diagonal elements are large,
are quite different from zero, then the very reason we need Markovitch is the same reason that Markovitch will fail.
So that's Markovitch's course. The more we need Markovitch, the more likely Markovitch is to fail.
Now, how common is it to observe in finance correlations of diagonal correlations that are significantly, significantly greater than zero?
Well, it's very common. When you think of clusters of securities identified with sector exposure, country exposure, region, size, as a result of all these common traits and factors, the securities will bundle together in clusters.
And these clusters mean that Markovits cannot differentiate between them.
When two securities are very similar, the portfolio optimization solution cannot differentiate between security I and security B, which means that even a small change in the expected return will fail.
optimization solution cannot differentiate between security I and security B, which means that even
a small change in the expected return will produce a large shift in the allocations.
So that's one way to understand how the previous linear algebra works in practice. In econometrics,
sometimes this is known as multicollinearity, right? When you have a system where the various
variables that they are trying to model are mutually correlated. And as I said,
this is very common in finance, so unless we deal with signal-induced instability,
Markovitch solutions are going to be very unstable. So this is where the NCO
algorithm comes in. NCO stands for nested cluster optimization. You can think of
this algorithm as five stages. In stage number one we find the optimal clusters
associated with the covariance matrix. So for that you can use the ONC algorithm
or you can use some other algorithm that identifies not only the optimal number
of clusters but their composition. Once you know what are the clusters this
allows you to partition the investment universe into several blocks. For each block, for each of
these clusters, you can optimize the clusters independently and in parallel. So let's say that
the system correctly identifies that there are 10 blocks, one for each sector, and now you can
produce one optimal portfolio for financials, another optimal portfolio for consumer discretionary,
for information technology, etc. And now that you have optimal performance for each cluster,
this allows you to go to stage three where you reduce the system. Instead of working with an
end-by-end system, now you will work with a k-by-k system where k is the number of clusters.
In stage number four, you can now compute the allocation between the clusters. So in this case,
it would be 10 by 10 convenience matrix. So now you can produce, you can estimate these weights
correctly 10 weights essentially And in stage number five you compute what is the allocation per security which is the dot product of the allocations intercluster and the allocations intracluster
So suppose that you know the weight for financials and then, you know, within financials, the weight for UBS.
Therefore, you know the weight for UBS, right, which is the product of the two optimal weights.
So why does this approach work better than Markovitch?
Well, it works better than Markovitch for a very simple reason.
We took a problem that was ill-defined, meaning that there was a covariance matrix with all of these high off-diagonal correlation values,
and we transform it into a reduced covariance matrix with one variable per cluster, where the off-diagonal elements must be very close to zero.
Why? Because if they were not close to zero, then the clusters would have emerged.
So, clustering in this sense allows us to compute a covariance matrix that is very close to a diagonal covariance matrix, and that's the ideal case for Markovitch.
So, essentially, we took a problem that was ill-defined, and we were able to cast it as a well-behaved problem, where Markovitch is going to work much better.
So, does this work?
Well, let's repeat the same experiment that we did before.
we are going to take a covariance matrix, let's say from Barra, and we are going to sample from
this covariance matrix many different empirical covariance matrices. We're going to compute the
solution for each of them. We will compare it with the solution that comes directly from
optimizing Barra without any sort of transformation, and that allows us to bootstrap
the estimation errors. So that's the standard approach how we evaluate estimation errors in
statistics. In this case instead of working with a 500 by 500 covariance matrix I'm going to work
with an even smaller covariance matrix 50 by 50 because what I want to show you is that even with
a small size problems signal induced instability is extremely problematic. So what we do here is
we take our minimum balance portfolio and we apply the NCO algorithm, we compare it
with Markovitch and what we get is a 47 reduction in the root mean square error Again very significant just as we saw with noise instability when we denoised the covariance matrix
What is very interesting about this result is that the shrinkage in this case,
as you can see, actually is detrimental.
The shrinkage makes the solution even more unstable.
Why is that?
Well, it makes sense. When we saw at the beginning of this presentation is that a shrinkage eliminates noise, but it also eliminates signal.
So when you're dealing with even a small size of investment universe, denoising can lead to an increase in the violence.
So one observation from this experiment is that do not take a shrinkage for granted.
Sometimes it will help and very often it will actually be detrimental.
NCO is helpful in both cases.
And when we go to the maximum sharp ratio portfolio, then we obtain a reduction in the root mean square of around 55%.
Now, let me conclude with a framework for estimating efficient frontiers that goes beyond what I just described in terms of denoising and the nested cluster algorithm.
We don't need to assume that there is an algorithm that will always be superior or that will always be beneficial.
In fact, if machine learning teaches us something, it's that there are some algorithms that are very good at the problem, but at the different problems there is another better algorithm.
And we should take this kind of experimental approach when we optimize portfolios in finance.
We should analyze what is the best optimization tool given a set of inputs.
So what I'm suggesting is that we repeat the same method that I described during this presentation twice.
We apply a Monte Carlo approach to derive what is the optimization method that is most beneficial for a particular problem So again we will take some inputs that could come from BARA or that you compute yourself We are going to
generate empirical convenience matrices and vectors of expected returns, given those inputs,
by drawing random observations from them.
And then we will apply these optimization methods,
whether it is Markovitch or NCO of hierarchical risk parity
or whatever approach that you think is a good candidate.
We will repeat these millions of times,
and this will allow us to estimate what is the estimation error
associated with each of these procedures,
given these set of inputs.
so this is the schema of how you would do it you could denoise or not depending on what you want
to try perhaps you denoise in some approaches and not in other approaches you collect all of
the information and eventually you will reach a conclusion with these inputs this is the best
approach i think that in general you will observe that the methods i describe here are extremely
helpful because they go really to the root cause of why markovit trails but there is no need to
assume this. We should let the evidence speak for itself. Well, I hope that you enjoyed this
presentation. If you like this subject and these topics, you will learn more about this in these
two publications. In particular, in this new book, Machine Learning for Asset Managers, you can
find the code associated with these experiments that I just mentioned. And with that, Thomas,
I give you the mic back and I look forward to your questions.
Yes. Thank you very much, Professor Marcus Lopez de Prado, for a great presentation.
I would like to remind all the attendees that there is a possibility to ask questions here.
If you look at below on your screen, there's a Q&A so you can type questions and then I can read them out here.
Just to start, I have received a couple of questions here while we wait for more questions from the audience.
You talk about denoise in the covariance matrix using machine learning.
So how about the noise in the expected return before adding it in the portfolio optimization?
Yes, absolutely.
So I focus on the covariance matrix because, as you can see from the problem, the covariance matrix needs to be inverted.
And this inversion is guaranteed to create instability.
that doesn't mean that there is also noise in the vector of expected returns.
And for that, you can conduct a shrinkage on that as well.
And that's where you have Stein estimators and so on.
So I agree.
I focus in this presentation on the shrinkage of the covariance matrix or denoising of certain eigenvalues.
But you could also observe an experiment with a shrinkage of the mu's.
Thank you. Let me see, we have one question here from the audience, from Laurence Finkels.
How can machine learning help to do variable selection to predict the direction of the stock or bond market?
Yes, in the presentation I've made today, this is an input, right?
We already have mu and we already have the covariance matrix.
So this is an input to this model.
But in general, what you could do is you could look into MDA kind of methods.
So the mean decrease accuracy method in particular is very helpful in machine learning to evaluate what are the variables associated with a phenomenon.
But there are other methods that are very helpful, too.
there's Shapley values, there's the line method, there's the PDP method.
So there are multiple approaches in machine learning that you can use in order to evaluate whether there is an important feature.
Now, let me tell you that this is really one of the strengths of machine learning that is not often understood.
When you think of classical statistics,
the fundamental way variables are selected is through p And the problem with p is that they rely on many relatively unrealistic assumptions at least unrealistic in finance
And as a result, p-values are not a very good indicator of whether a variable is truly
involved in the phenomenon or not. And there are plenty of studies that discuss
p-hacking and p-value inflation associated with all of the evaluation of all of these assumptions.
Fortunately, in machine learning we have more experimental methods that do not rely on all of
these assumptions. So I would recommend you to read the first book I cited at the end of my
presentation, Advances in Financial Machine Learning, where you will find many examples
of how to do variable selection in finance.
Thank you.
Let me see.
We have another question here.
It's regarding the signal-induced noise.
Would you agree that when we adjust the returns using an index as S&P 500,
we are incorporating noise from an index that is not optimal?
That could be the case.
typically when you introduce
a benchmark or some biases, in fact, there could be
some benefits. So it's not necessarily
true that when you incorporate some biases, as a result
the system is going to be unstable. In fact, if you remember from
statistics, there is something called the bias-biance trade-off.
And sometimes you may want to introduce
biases on purpose in order to reduce the mean square error of the estimator. So I would say
experiment. Take your approach, run it following the method, the Monte Carlo
paradigm that I described here, and see what the results are and experiment. It will be very hard
to reach a conclusion as to whether introducing some form of bias or not is going to be detrimental.
Sometimes it will but if the system is extremely noisy in fact adding some bias may be helpful to reduce the root being a square error Thank you We have one more question here from Alexandre Rubissant He says
the clustering approach you mentioned is very intuitive
in the context of a stock portfolio. Would you please comment
on the challenges of applying this approach to a multi-asset
class portfolio? Well, for a multi-asset class,
instead of using a classing method, you could use a
different approach. You could use, for instance,
a knowledge graph. In a knowledge graph,
think of a knowledge graph as a modern covariance matrix
where you can evaluate how various securities are interconnected
and you can identify what is the minimum
spanning tree associated with that knowledge graph. And that's going to give you essentially
the various clusters. So that would be another approach that is not just based on the clustering
of the correlation matrix. Another method would be instead of clustering the correlation matrix,
you could do clustering on the distance matrix derived from the mutual information between the
securities. So instead of looking for linear codependence, what you could do is you could
apply information theory to estimate what is the mutual information between the securities
and then use the distance between these securities as derived from mutual information to cluster.
So there are various ways in which you can generalize this approach to beyond clustering
of a correlation matrix. Thank you. Let's see, another question here is, we all know bad data
equals bad models. What recent advances have you seen in data sources? I know some quant funds have
access to aggregate debit and credit card spending data for predicting quarterly results in retail,
for example, Amazon. Yes, so data is one of the most exciting areas of progress. Three years ago
these data sets didn't exist, right? When you think of credit card transactions or microlending or
or whether it is email receipts, information that comes from manufacturing and engineering processes.
So there are today tons of observations And in a sense this old framework where everybody just used a correlation matrix is today very limited right And that why
in the previous question I referred to knowledge graphs. So my
suggestion is that rather than relying on the old
data, we all pay attention and take a look at the new
sources and we experiment with these new sources. So in the previous question
we tackle how to optimize the portfolio of multiple asset classes.
Well, to understand the connection between multiple asset classes,
perhaps the correlation matrix is too limited.
So instead of using a correlation matrix, we use a knowledge graph,
and we understand the codependences.
Sometimes they are synchronous, sometimes asynchronous codependences
between the various variables.
And we use that information to model their mutual relationship.
So that would be an approach that is based on alternative data. Why? Because it's not simply based on running regressions and computing correlations.
We're going to incorporate information that comes from more advanced estimators, machine learning algorithms,
but also information that comes from the analysis of these securities.
these securities. You see, when we compute a correlation matrix, we just run some estimators
and we utilize that information and we cannot really manipulate the correlation matrix, right?
We change some value that we think is extreme. As a result, the correlation matrix is going to turn
inconsistent and it's not going to be useful. But a very good advantage of machine learning is that,
in fact these approaches are open and transparent. We can modify the knowledge
graph and that's not going to break the model. We can actually incorporate
information, a priori information that we know about the knowledge graph and
follow through the method. So in conclusion, yes we should definitely use
all of these data sources and when we do so in a machine learning framework we
align them in a particular way, like for instance when we compute a correlation matrix.
Thank you.
Another question here is, what do you think about using filtering
methods to remove noise from financial data? Are they not
powerful enough to solve noise problems that you mentioned?
Yes, they are. Look, you could use, for instance, a Kalamann filter
to try to smooth sound returns.
and I think that's a good idea
you should always experiment
so the fact that Kalman filter works very well
in some fields it doesn't mean that it's going to work well
in finance, you should try Kalman filter
you should try
Stein shrinkage, you should use
Ledouin-Wolfe shrinkage, you should use denoising
and experiment, run Monte Carlo experiments
to see what approaches are
exhibit better mathematical properties given the set of inputs
and the size of the problem that you are tackling.
I think we have time for one more last question here.
That is, how can machine learning be applied in
empirical asset pricing? That is, choosing the optimal investment
factors in the dynamic model and to explain why investment strategies
work or don't work. Yes, so this
a huge topic. I will refer to you to the first book I mentioned at the end of the presentation,
Advances in Financial Machine Learning, where I describe machine learning methods that are useful
in the context of time series analysis, right? And that's really the main difference between
the problems we analyze in finance compared to other problems like, for instance,
face recognition or problems associated with
with national language programming, sentiment structure, et cetera.
When we deal with a prediction, price prediction in finance, we care about the time series.
And we cannot assume that the observations are associated with IID processes,
and very often the features will not be stationary, et cetera.
So there are all of these characteristics of financial problems that are not in compliance with the basic assumptions of machine learning.
And that why I discuss financial machine learning as a field in its own right We need to tackle issues of time dependence and non that are quite peculiar in finance
And in the case of price prediction, all of this matters because we will have to deal with the fact that some prices exhibit cointegration and some prices exhibit a terascadasticity that there is serial conditionality in the observation.
So it is a huge topic and there are no easy solutions, but some methods seem to work better than others.
And that's what I discuss in that book.
Yeah, well, thank you. Thank you very much. I guess that brings us to the end of the presentation.
It's really been an honor having you here. So thank you very much for being here with us today and telling us about or presenting your research, answering the questions.
Thank you. My absolute pleasure. And stay safe. Thank you.
Thanks.
So then that brings us to
The next part of our
Of the program
We will have the final of our call for papers
So about a month ago
We sent out the call
For the call for papers
Related to the subject
which Professor Marcus Lopez-Aprado has been talking about.
It's related to machine learning for asset management.
We have the jury here with us.
The jury has read all of the papers, and we have selected four finalists.
The four finalists will each shortly present their paper in a five-minute pitch,
followed by a five-minute Q&A session.
After that, we will select the winner.
The winner will receive a prize of 20,000 Norwegian kroner and the opportunity to be part of a NURQUANT internship.
We have a jury here.
The jury here consists of Alberto Guillen Jimenez He head of analysis at Nordquant and formerly responsible for factor strategies at Norwegian Bank Investment Management We have Professor Laurence Finkels
He's a research director at Rubico and professor at Erasmus University in Rotterdam.
He's also a board member of our association, Norsk Forening for Quantitative Finance.
Joining us online, we have Kersti Oas.
She is a director of Norsk Reinecentral and also a board member of our association.
And we have Bo Letran.
He's a researcher at Noord University.
So the four finalists that we will be hearing from today, it's in a random order,
but this is the order that we will ask them to present their papers.
First of all, we will be hearing from Eirik E. Selander.
The name of his paper is Measuring the Importance of Asset Pricing Factors Using Machine Learning.
After that, we will hear from Signe Kilsgaard.
She will be talking about aksjeutvelgelse ved bruk av random forests.
The paper is in Norwegian, but the presentation will be in English.
thirdly we will be hearing from a paper
written by two
students
it's Mons Eile
and David Fang
the name of their paper is
Evaluating Value at Risk and ES
for Commodities both conventionally
and with Neural Networks
the last presentation
will be from Emilia
Alarcon she will
present her paper
Cryptocurrency Market Returns
So then let's get started with our first presenter.
This is Eirik Selander.
Thank you.
Let me share the screen.
Yeah, I guess I have to share the screen here with you now.
Yes.
Can you see the screen?
Yes, we see it here.
Okay.
Go ahead.
All right.
So, yeah, hello, everyone.
My name is Erik Zalander, and I'm going to present my dissertation, as mentioned, titled
Measuring the Importance of Asset Pricing Factors Using Machine Learning So I start by discussing the problem the methodology look at the findings and then finally the contributions and implications of the paper So one of the great problems in
empirical asset pricing, this was already alluded to previously, but just estimating conditional
expected stock returns. Now, given that this is a prediction exercise, it would be interesting to
know which variables are important for this prediction problem.
So that's one of the motivations.
Now the other one is from a more of a practitioner's point of view.
So there are some evidence showing that the correlations of asset prices have increased
over time.
And if that's the case, then it will be useful to have a system that can continuously look
for predictive signals.
and also given the increased saturation in the markets,
it also makes it important to look for predictive signals continuously.
So the research question is then,
which variables have the greatest impact on the prediction of stock returns?
Now, why should we use machine learning for this?
Traditional models have struggled to do this
when you have a high number of variables.
And also when there are non-linearities, so models like linear regressions can struggle in these situations.
Machine learning allows for this.
I'll discuss this in further detail in the paper.
And we can do this now because of the increased data availability and computing power.
Now, I look at data from Japan, the US, UK and Norway over the following 28-year period.
I use monthly frequency and I look at 42 predictor variables.
Now I focus on firm characteristics and price signals in this paper.
And the methodology I use is I test six models listed here.
And then I measure the variable importance, which is the main issue, is I look at permutation importance and SHAP values for robustness.
so
um the most exciting oh sorry and then to my approach is to look at first the most accurate
models for these data sets so we can get kind of an accurate description of the variable importance
now these are the variables i look at and i test some new variables as well
which are listed here these are all available in the paper so the findings firstly i find that
that bagging, random forest, and gradient boosting achieve the highest accuracy across all the geographies and all the data sets.
These are all nonlinear models, so it kind of makes sense to what was mentioned previously.
And in terms of the variables, I find that price signals of various kinds like momentum and return volatility are highly predictive.
lowest predictive categories
accounting ratios
there are some
kind of
deviations to this so earnings yield is okay
but still the overall
price signals do the best
so the only difference
from other papers were that
liquidity factors
didn't do as well in my paper as compared to
some recent papers
however the findings are robust across countries and after redoing
analysis with the alternative measure of variable importance
the SHAP values now what are the key takeaways
it's a generic framework and it's easily applicable to other settings so
hedge funds and asset managers can use this approach
for to investigate other data sources like macroeconomic variables like GDP
and employment interest rate or alternative data like social media feeds, satellite images.
And the code is kind of easily put into a Jupyter notebook so the user could just change the data source
and then just redo the analysis and get signals continuously.
So in the paper, I go through kind of some applications.
application.
So I
construct,
sorry,
this is a
bit small,
but I
construct some
factor portfolios,
both single
factor and multi portfolios and I look at the kind of change over time compared to the market index And then I look at the correlations of the different portfolios
between the returns of each portfolio. So they can be used for kind of factor tilting and things
like this. I also look at the Sharpe ratios and the rolling Sharpe ratios over time.
So let's go through.
So just to conclude, so it contributes to the literature by, so it's kind of a growing literature of testing machine learning models and testing variable importance for machine learning for financial applications.
So I contribute to this literature by testing for geographical differences of recent findings,
because most of them use similar or the same data sets from the US.
So I wanted to see if it held up using a different data set.
I test eight new predictor variables.
And I confirm the price signal findings from a lot of the recent papers mentioned here.
so in general
I think
this kind of research gives insight
into the statistical
processes that drive stock returns
and gives kind of insight into that black box
and so we can give some economic rationale
and it provides investors
with useful modeling tools
and as was mentioned already
as well noisy nature
of stock markets
poses a challenge to retest to get predictive signals over time.
So lastly, I'm sure I'm harming on time, but
last I just wanted to mention some things that can be looked at for future
research that weren't necessarily looked at in my paper, but that are
relevant. So, you know, how has the
variable importance changed over time? Sampling frequency, because
obviously some data sources are sampled at different
frequency.
So, you know, accounting ratios are less updated than the prices, transactions costs.
I didn't use deep learning in my paper, so that would be something to look at.
And then as Professor Di Prado is working on I know is kind of developing more custom machine learning algorithms that are more custom made for financial applications
That's it. So thank you.
Yeah, no, thank you. Thank you very much for a very interesting presentation.
Then we switch over to the jury.
that we have here with us.
Are there any questions about this presentation?
Yes, Laurens?
Yes, I have a question.
In your paper, I think you highlighted more than during the presentation
that one-month momentum is one of the strongest factors
that you find in your procedure.
So now I was not completely sure because the literature,
for example, in 1990,
90 they find a strong reversal at the one month horizon so the opposite of momentum so is it
um that you find also a reversal so a negative sign for this one month momentum or do you find
the opposite results so really a positive momentum results in for the sample that you look at
so yeah i think for my case it would be an opposite finding i am familiar i'm not
I'm not sure if I'm familiar with that particular paper, but from the paper I listed here.
So you were first in Jack Deacon-Tipman, I think, in the thesis at least.
Yes, sorry. So, yeah, that was based on kind of where the momentum factor was first kind of introduced.
But in terms of the findings, I think some of these papers listed here find similar, that momentum has a high predictive signal.
I suppose the finding you mentioned there
is a bit different here
Thank you very much
Now we will proceed with the next presentation
which will be Signe Kjeldskap
presenting on a paper
titled Stop Selection with Use of Random Forests
Please Signe
Okay, I'll just have to share my screen, let's see.
Okay so first of all I want to thank you for letting me participate My name is Simna and I going to present to you my paper which is titled Stock Selection using Random Forest a machine learning approach
So my study implements the machine learning method Random Forest for stock selection.
The purpose is to examine whether the method is capable of discovering patterns that contribute to excess returns in the Norwegian stock market, based on both technical and fundamental features.
Okay, so between approximately December 2010 and May 2019, I select 10 stocks for an equally
weighted portfolio at each rebalancing day, which are based on probability rankings from
the Random Forest Model.
In total, I construct three portfolios to check how robust this method is.
The first portfolio, which is my main portfolio, is created for a long holding period based on both technical and fundamental features.
And the other two portfolios are created for a short holding period of one day.
And the first of these two is based on also the combined feature space of both technical and fundamental features.
And the second of these two portfolios is a pure momentum portfolio.
All three of these portfolios generate significant excess returns before transaction costs, and
they greatly outperform the OCBX, which is the benchmark, when these costs are not taken
into consideration.
Before transaction costs, the portfolios achieve sharp ratios of 2.14, 5.13, and 5.55.
For the portfolios with the long holding portfolio, which is my main portfolio, the transaction
costs are not that high, so the performance is still high after transaction costs.
But for the portfolios with the short holding periods, the returns are drastically reduced
after transaction costs because they have a high daily turnover.
portfolio returns are not stable over time. And when looking at the trend, it does show a decreasing
time over trend over time, which is present in all the three portfolios. And there's also in
line with previous research that my studies based on. So this could be a result of the increased
popularity of machine learning techniques. Potential does, however, not seem to disappear
over the period. In addition to generating portfolios, I also check for
variable importances from the training data sets and these illustrate that there
is a relationship between the selected features and the returns. So this figure
shows the variable importances for the portfolio with the long holding period.
So for the long holding period, the long-term technical features as well as
as some of the top fundamental features here are the most important ones.
In the Norwegian market, it does seem that especially volatility is an important feature for returns,
and this applies to both the long holding period and the short holding period with the combined feature space.
For the short-term momentum strategy, the most important price movements for the returns
that seem to be the ones in the days prior to the stock selection,
as well as more long-term price movements.
When these variable importances are seen in relation with the returns,
these results from my study must be said to pose the challenge
to both the weak and the semi-strong form of market efficiency.
So let's see.
During approximately nine and a half years of the trading period,
The selected stocks for my portfolios mainly contribute positively to portfolio returns.
So this table shows the top 10 selected stocks for the portfolio with a long holding period
and shows that on average, these stocks contribute with an average monthly return of 8.1%.
And this proves that the model is both robust and reliable at generating positive returns.
Just to provide some concluding remarks my study shows that the random forest model has potential for generating excess returns in the Norwegian market for both the short and the long holding periods This means that there is potential for profitability with the use of machine learning techniques
that discover and exploit patterns in financial data.
When I ignore transaction costs, the potential is especially high for the short holding period,
but the profitability is, however, extremely dependent on being able to get low transaction costs
for these portfolios as they have high daily turnovers.
So machine learning techniques and particularly random forest that I look at
should be of interest and be useful for both traders and portfolio managers
as it not only helps in generating returns,
but it also helps to illustrate important patterns for the data.
So, yeah, thank you.
I hope you've heard that.
Okay, thank you
I have a question
you showed that you find
sharp ratios that are
between 2 and 5
after the
teaching, so that sounds
almost too good to be true
to me
I was just wondering, could it be that you are
making use of some
let's say information
with hindsight that you would not
really have in real time
or that you do some data finding
to get these good results?
I have adjusted all my data
so it should not use anything
that is not available at the time.
My method, it doesn't have a function.
It assumes that I can buy it twice
and sell it twice.
Some parts of my methodology
would not be entirely able to do
in the Norwegian market as it is now.
However, it does follow the methodology
of other studies that showed similar results and the extreme high results sharp ratios from the
portfolios with the short holding period is due to the transaction costs. So using transaction costs
I think the ones that are given to a regular investor the strategy will not be
be able to give those
active returns So those strategies are dependent on getting especially low transaction costs to be able to be profitable Okay thank you very much Signe
So now we move on to the next work,
which was authored by Måns Eile and David Fang.
Yeah, so please, Måns, go ahead.
Okay, thank you very much.
So since it's two of us and we have a limited time of five minutes, I will be conducting the presentation and then we will both answer your questions.
So let me just share my screen here.
Okay, so our master's thesis then is called Evaluating Value at Risk and Expected Shortfall for Commodities, both Conventionally and with Neural Networks.
And briefly then an agenda for this presentation is an introduction to the subject and a brief section about the data and methodology and then the conclusions of the thesis, especially for the ANL part.
So as we all know, risk management is becoming increasingly important in asset management.
It is one of the most important factors in delivering sustainable and high returns over long periods of time.
And within this area of research, the most commonly researched assets have been stocks and bonds.
So we actually found commodities to be an interesting asset class to investigate.
As it offers diversification means, it often has low or negative correlation to stocks.
And furthermore, the volatility pattern of commodities is deviating somewhat from traditional assets
in its high and sometimes extreme volatility with clustering properties, as well as nonlinear properties.
So the conventional way in modeling and forecasting clustering volatility has been the GARCH 1-1 approach,
where the volatility forecast of tomorrow depends on today's volatility as well as today's unexpected deviation.
However, the inherent drawback of the GARCH-1-1 is that it is not model-free,
meaning that it imposes an explicit relationship onto the data.
And especially when we see nonlinear properties of the volatility as we do for commodities,
it can sometimes be hard to find a conjunction that very well fits the volatilities So therefore we looked at an alternative machine learning approach namely the artificial neural network as it has great predictive abilities and is very well
specified to map non-linearities and complex data sets. And more specifically, we looked at the
long short-term memory as it is very well specified for sequential or time series data.
And then again, the main advantage of the artificial neural network is that it is
completely model-free, so there is no pre-specified relationship, which in this case should work
very well.
So then about the data and methodology, the commodities examined were oil, gold, and soybean,
as these are three of the most traded commodities within their respective sectors.
Oil has amongst the highest volatility out of all commodities and is the most produced
and traded.
Gold has often been seen as a hedging mean to the stock market that rises in times of uncertainty.
And soybean is one of the most traded agricultural commodities.
So the time period evaluated was 30 years between 1990 and 2019 due to the start date of the indices examined.
And so then the volatility estimates received by the ANN and the GARCH-1-1 were utilized in a volatility-weighted historical simulation to conduct the VARN ES estimates for each day in the testing period.
And then they were evaluated against the loss of that day.
And so for the ANN, the only predictor of future volatility was daily realized volatility.
So that was the sole predictor.
And this approach was carried out for three different confidence levels of value at risk and expected shortfall, 95%, 97.5% and 99%.
And then we utilized three different tests.
The QPX test to test the amount of bar violations received against expected amount.
The Christofferson's independence test to test the independence of the violations and to see that they're not too clustered together.
And finally, the testing ES directly test introduced by Akribi and Sikli in 2014
that tests for the average bar exceedance, which is the same as testing for expected shortfall.
And then for our conclusions, even though the data set was on the small side
artificial neural networks with only approximately 7,500 realized volatility observations.
It did overall perform remarkably well with well-specified bar and ES estimates that passed
26 out of the 27 tests, with one exception being QPX test for gold on a 95% confidence level.
It did outperform the GARCH-1-1 in terms of forecasting accuracy, as could be seen by a
lower mean squared error, and mean average error.
So since the network implemented had somewhat of a simpler architecture
with realized volatility being the only predictor,
we do see great potential to scale the network
when time and computing power is not as limited.
We basically computed the network on our laptops.
So in its forecasting prowess, we do see potential to implement
more complex neural networks in forecasting volatility of other asset classes,
as well as forecasting prices.
So thank you so much for listening, and we now welcome your questions.
Yeah, thank you.
Okay, thank you.
In the Apparel application, it seems you used two spot indices
and one access return on futures-based and durables-based index,
if I remember correctly.
Yeah.
Since you do not
trade in large quantities in spot rates
and futures prices
can move differently from spot
prices, was there a
specific reason to look at
spot prices or would you
expect that the results you have also
carry over to
future contracts, forward contracts?
Go on.
Okay.
So actually, it's kind of funny because when we were sorting the data from Bloomberg,
we found that it didn't provide a total return or excess return for all of the commodities that we wanted to investigate.
So first of all, in the beginning, we saw this as a problem.
However, we did examine the goal that had both the excess return and the spot return index.
And we saw that they were highly similar.
So even though of course the futures price can be weighed from the pay price we still think that it should be viable I think this spot price was only used for one of the commodities and the excess returns were awarded to others So ideally
we would want to take all futures for
X return indices, but I still think that the
results are viable.
Thank you very much. And with this we will move on
the last presentation yeah it would be emilia alarcon presenting a work named understanding
cryptocurrency market returns yeah this is emilia yes hello um
okay
Okay. So my name is Emilia D'Arcon and I will present understanding and predicting cryptocurrency market returns.
The potential for making profits investing in cryptocurrency, the hedging benefits and their role,
not only in global economy, but also in the digital future,
make it relevant to study the determinants of cryptocurrencies and analyze different returns prediction models.
Recent studies have focused on one or some cryptocurrency.
This study will analyze the cryptocurrency market as a whole.
The purposes are to identify the determinants of the cryptocurrency market and to find a returns prediction model.
For this, machine learning techniques that have gained a lot of attention because of their prediction accuracy will be used.
A dataset including all cryptocurrencies was extracted.
It was observed that 11 cryptocurrencies with largest market capitalization represent 90%
of the total market.
Therefore, these 11 cryptocurrencies are used to calculate a cap weighted index, which is
transformed to returns and is the response variable for this study.
Okay. The explanatory variables are 41 features that are divided in cryptocurrency market data, information demand, commodities, exchange rates, financial markets, and macroeconomics.
Determining the methods to be used in this study the trade between interpretability and prediction was considered Lasso being less flexible than least squares is also more interpretable and is therefore
selected to find the determinants for the cryptocurrency market.
In this case, the features and the returns will be analyzed in the same day to see the
immediate relationship.
For prediction, it is known that more flexible methods can give better predictions if the
the relationship between the predictors and the response is nonlinear.
Therefore, different levels of flexibility are tested using LASSO, regression trees, random forest, and boosting trees.
And in this case, data in the inputs, one day before data in the inputs is used,
and the last value of the returns is included in the model.
And according to the variables selected by LASSO for prediction, a new data set is constructed.
So all the methods in prediction will be tested in the all predictors data set and in the last of predictors data set.
And then these models will be compared using the test mean square error being the method,
the model with the lowest test mean square error, the one that has best prediction accuracy.
The results show that analyzing the features and the returns in the same day, LASSO selected
14 features from the 41 used.
This includes cryptocurrency market data, the high, low, open market cap lag, and volume.
Also some stock market indexes as the Dow Jones, NASDAQ, and IMOX.
The commodities as gold, gas, and oil as well with a lower effect in the returns.
the exchange rate, dollar to rubble, and the volatility index, VIX.
For prediction, LASA found that five variables have prediction power.
These are the dollar to Chinese yuan exchange rate, the stock market indexes, the Nikkei and the BSE, market cap, and gas.
and comparing prediction performance
between the models used
it can be seen that random forest
with all the predictors data set
is the one with the lowest test mean square error
followed by random forest
with the lasso predictors data set
then it's boosting
lasso and regression trees so the cryptocurrency market variables are the most important determinants of the cryptocurrency market returns
The stock market indexes, Dow Jones, Nasdaq, and IMOX have a positive relationship with the returns,
implying that the hedging benefits of cryptocurrencies have to be carefully considered.
Gold affect the returns positively and the dollar to rubble exchange rate negatively.
And gas and oil seem to have a low effect in the cryptocurrency market.
Regarding prediction, the dollar to Chinese yuan exchange rate emerged as the most important determinant.
The model with lowest test mean square error was Random Forest with all the predictors data set.
So this can be a model that can be used to predict the cryptocurrency market returns,
suggesting also a nonlinear relationship between the predictors and the response.
Boosting did not outperform random forest.
This could be because cross-validation was used to determine the tuning parameters for boosting,
and boosting may have overfitted the data, which random forest didn't do.
Thank you.
Thank you very much, Amelia. I don't know if we have some questions from Jury.
Yes, I have a question about, you used 11 cryptocurrencies and when,
at what period in time did you select them? Because I'm a bit worried that when you select
the largest cryptocurrencies at the end of the sample period, that those were not necessarily
the largest cryptocurrencies in real time.
So there's some survivorship bias in the return of the index
that you're trying to predict.
Is that a possibility?
Yeah, I selected 11 cryptocurrencies in May, the 1st of May,
and that's where I found the ones that had the largest market capitalization.
So at that time, I selected the 11 cryptocurrencies,
Yes, so they were selected at my first...
At the first data point or at the last data point?
The last data point.
Okay.
Thanks.
And another question is, you have analyzed an index of cryptocurrencies.
Have you happened to analyze individual cryptocurrencies from your methodology?
No, I didn't.
I calculated with these 11 cryptocurrencies with largest market capitalization,
I calculated an index according to the KPM portfolio determination,
where assets are weighted according to the presence in the market.
So this was the index that I used during all the study.
I didn't analyze each currency individually.
Thank you very much, Emilia.
and thank you very much
to all the
presenters
as well as all the other
submitters
it has been
a very
high level among the finalists
and
all of them
could be a winner
so
the jury has voted
and I must
say that by a very small margin so all the four finalists are actually really good But by a small margin so we have a winner and then the jury has decided the award of
20,000 Norwegian crowns as well as an opportunity to take an internship at Nurkwand has been
awarded to Signe Kirskar for her work on stock selection using random forests.
so congratulations to the winner
also thank you very much for all the participants
and yeah
so with this we conclude our seminar
yes thank you very much
thank you for the jury
I think it was a great presentation
four very interesting papers
and we have a winner which we will contact afterwards
thank you all for attending
and we hope this will be the first one of many webinars for our association,
and of course that we will be starting with seminars again when that's a possibility.
So thank you very much.
We end the webinar here.
Thank you.
you